[SPEAKER_02]: I'm thinking about mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, the difference between, like, thinking that you need to constantly, like, not even going into the contemporary views of what mindfulness is, but even the idea that you need to be, like, constantly rehearsing ideas and stuff, and, you know, however accurate they are, you know, suttas and whatnot, versus just
[SPEAKER_02]: The ability to sort of...
[SPEAKER_02]: I was trying to think of a good way to put it earlier, but kind of just chuck something in the back, so to speak, and know that it'll be there when it is necessary.
[SPEAKER_02]: Namely, well, to give an example, just, like, if you notice that there are certain circumstances where you're more likely to act out unwholesomely, you don't need to, like, be reminding yourself of that throughout the day.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, like, like, you don't need to be constantly going over it, because there's...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how would you prevent yourself from acting out if you're constantly reminding yourself?
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you just... That's kind of where I wanted to bring the conversation, is... Like, it's obvious that there are things that you just remember when they're relevant, but there are also things you don't remember when it's relevant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what's the difference there?
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's not just coming
[SPEAKER_00]: So, but is it like that you just remember random facts and they stay there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I can just, I don't know, think about the age of the universe and then keep that at the back of my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that the type of context that we're talking about or is there a reason why you're able to keep certain things in mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, to answer your question, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not just random facts.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's more, I guess, what that leads me to think of is, when you encounter something that you're familiar with, you'll have ideas about it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether those ideas are, this is something I should do, this is something I shouldn't do, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but then,
[SPEAKER_00]: But that would be like, you encounter things, but that would be like a very particular kind of, let's say, a particular event.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's not like the mindfulness should be there only at those times, because, strictly speaking, all the time you have something happening.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, so, you might kind of bring up the mindfulness in those specific moments that will prevent you from kind of acting out too much.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you also want to have mindfulness
[SPEAKER_03]: Pretty much constantly, in a way, because constantly you have the possibility of greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it might be there to lesser extents than you kind of anticipate, but any extent, fundamentally, you have to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how could you make sure that you don't allow room for those, you know, lesser forms of those kind of completely proliferated acting out of greed and stuff, that you still
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep those things in check without constantly having to remind yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, again, like, remembering random facts... Everybody knows, of course, that's not going to work.
[SPEAKER_03]: And random facts doesn't just have to be things about the world.
[SPEAKER_03]: It can also be, like, information, like, kind of, that you heard from someone.
[SPEAKER_03]: Those things can be useful to point you to what to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: But fundamentally, those are just kind of, like, if you just get Alzheimer's, you forget.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, this isn't quite answering your question yet, but just spinning off a little bit of what you said that you may bring us there.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, I guess, what I sort of had in mind was, as you're refining your idea of what is an unwholesome mental state, you kind of get these ideas like, yeah, it's obviously not about the, like, physical
[SPEAKER_02]: You kind of get these... you can get more subtle pictures of what it looks like when your mind is in one of these states.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, I guess, I'm kind of falling into the, like, taking that and saying, oh, that's not... that's different.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not also just an appearance.
[SPEAKER_02]: When it sort of is, it's just more of a
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, almost the appearance of what you take your mind to be, and you're kind of saying, okay, when that's there, then it's bad.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's the point, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: You want to... you're going to have some preconceived notion, but you want to upgrade that preconceived notion to correspond closer and closer to the root of the unwholesome mental state.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because everybody knows, like, when they kind of
[SPEAKER_03]: Find themselves shouting to someone, like they know, oh, I'm angry.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's your metric for what it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's a factual metric, you know.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, okay, clearly, when this happens, there's an angry mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But obviously, that's not going to be enough to uproot anger at its core.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that's where you notice.
[SPEAKER_03]: Some people, of course, do emphasizing the wrong things, emphasizing focusing techniques and stuff.
[SPEAKER_03]: They would never actually go beyond that conception of what anger is.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, only when I am angrily talking to someone, I'm angry.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, therefore, factually, it might feel like if I just speak in a certain way, I'm not angry anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: But no, it's like, there's this whole entire layer behind your speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, why are you talking to this person?
[SPEAKER_00]: As we said many times before, even if you're talking in the most lovely kind of voice, there's a mental state there, that's getting you to do that, without which you probably otherwise wouldn't be doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be annoyed, talking someone nicely, out of that annoyance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the appearance of that annoyance, that is not anymore as coarse as you're shouting at someone, is what you want to
[SPEAKER_00]: For you, now, that needs to become the notion of what an angry mind is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, eventually, what you're taking, like, what you're seeing for that, could eventually just be another... like, that could be... need refinement further.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eventually, you get used to that and then...
[SPEAKER_00]: But, obviously, now that all that refinement would be mental, like, it would just be more discerning further.
[SPEAKER_03]: indications like that simile of the of the king like um initially maybe you need to see him like make a certain movement like when he it doesn't say it just makes a certain movement or makes a certain facial expression when he's seeing the food but then you
[SPEAKER_00]: You start to discern even more peripheral things, like, I don't know, things that are not anymore as explicit.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a refinement of your discernment of this side of the line.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, whichever, to go back to the question of mindfulness, whichever level of refinement you have, why is it that you can
[SPEAKER_00]: Be mindful of things such as that, and an wholesome mental state, or a wholesome mental state, and not your random facts.
[SPEAKER_03]: What's the difference?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, you know, like, I, I, if you can maintain a certain mindfulness of, like, my mind is angry, and you wouldn't be able to to forget that unless
[SPEAKER_03]: You get careless and get involved with that angry mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: You mean still, like, on the level of not fully seeing the signs of the mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, let's say you see it to some extent.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's say... Like, you have an idea.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's not just, like, the course I'm yelling at somebody.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whatever extent you have... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's say you see the mind is angry right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it that you could stay mindful of that, but not, like, just mindful of what's gonna happen tomorrow or something?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's present.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not having to create the fact that... something just irrelevant to your experience, like the number of rings Saturn has.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why the satipaṭṭhānas are...
[SPEAKER_00]: They are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's why they are...
[SPEAKER_00]: The right mindfulness is defined as the satipaṭṭhānas, not as just kind of remembering
[SPEAKER_03]: Anything in a certain way.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's remembering these specific things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, of course, when I say specific, I don't mean like you focus on them.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, these are things that inevitably, regardless of how far you go, regardless of how you travel, what you're thinking about, how special you are,
[SPEAKER_03]: These things, these are the four kind of cornerstones of your experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: They have to be there all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you can develop mindfulness of these things because they are already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like you're already conscious of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Consciousness is not awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Consciousness is just the fact that the thing is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... You don't need to generate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, because of that...
[SPEAKER_03]: In order to keep yourself mindful.
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically, your awareness will be occupied with wrong things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, things that you're also conscious of, you can't be aware of something without being conscious of it, but you want to then make sure that your awareness applies to those relevant things, rather than just getting scattered into concerns that are secondary, that actually take you away from those foundations of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you're established in those,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when you can rightly say that only an intentional choice of forgetting will result in forgetting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you are conscious of these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, even if you don't want them to be there, they're there.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it were something else, like a random fact,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a... it's a... it's a volitional thing that you brought up and then the intention to think about it fades and then it disappears.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like you can, like, very earnestly think, I'm gonna do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, and very earnestly, very earnestly, like when people have, let's say, something very important for them to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then they continuously kind of keep in mind, like, oh, I have to do this, I have to do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or just trying to study, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's probably a better example.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you want to keep this stuff in mind because you have an exam or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: But factually, it just goes away.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't just forget that, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can cease to be conscious of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like... it's not a... it's not a concrete phenomenon that's there all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when it comes to these four foundations, whether you remember what you were studying or not, your body will still be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll still feel a certain way.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll still be in a certain mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... you'll still have phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is...
[SPEAKER_02]: This is where kind of adopting a first-person point of view is quite important.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you could say like, oh, well, you still factually have the test.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if you get Alzheimer's and, like, factually you don't know about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's very different than saying factually you still have a body.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you are taking on that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, like, factually you don't.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's why... that's how then mindfulness becomes effortless.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't become something that you do.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like you... like you said... what was the comparison you said?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like you throw something... Just kind of toss it in the back.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But see, it has to be something that's already at the back for that to work.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_03]: It can't just be...
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't just be a random thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that even that you're tossing it at the back.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like you have to see that it's already at the back, whether you toss it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the only way that it's gonna become established.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, from that perspective, it's gonna feel like, if you fall away from it, you're kind of descending down from a knowledge that was already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're descending down into further activity and proliferation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereas, if it's the other way around, if your mindfulness is something that you're doing, then that's now your... your mindfulness is your proliferation, is your, eh... engagement.
[SPEAKER_04]: If, eh... if those four phenomena aren't, eh...
[SPEAKER_04]: If it's not possible to rightly discern them, in the sense of having right view, um...
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: The thing is, you have to be trying to discern them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how you get the right view.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, I wanted to ask, what would be the closest thing to right mindfulness then, in the practice, basically?
[SPEAKER_04]: Tell us about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, in a way, first of all, yeah, keeping in mind, you haven't still understood them,
[SPEAKER_03]: Or understood how to discern them, for as long as you don't have the right view.
[SPEAKER_03]: That should be kind of before whatever mindfulness you're trying to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you do it on the basis of that, then it becomes a different, whole different thing, because you're actually trying to upgrade whatever you're doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not taking it for granted anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: So,
[SPEAKER_03]: It's quite another form of mindfulness that a person could have.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, no matter what novelty kind of developments occur in their practice, staying mindful of the fact that they're still liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that liability is a factual thing as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: You feel that threat.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, if certain things were to happen to me, my mind is in such a place that it would suffer quite a bit.
[SPEAKER_03]: And in and of itself, if you
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, Sut does even say, like, he knows a mind that is not liberated, is a mind that is not liberated.
[SPEAKER_03]: And factually, that would bring you closer to liberation, rather than then trying to fabricate what you think liberation is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because liberation comes out of precisely ignorance, like not not understanding these fundamental phenomena.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you were to develop that clear awareness, in the right sense,
[SPEAKER_03]: of a mind that's liable to suffering, you would remove the necessary basis or the fuel that was causing that suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: It might not disappear right away, but when you're aware of your liability to suffering, you won't be doing certain things anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can just take it on that on that very general level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's because of ignoring the fact that I'm still alive and suffering, this problem is still here, that you become heedless and just do things that undermine your own goal.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, let's let's try to explain that then.
[SPEAKER_03]: What would be the difference between... because it could easily just be an abstract fact.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just sit down and I say, okay, I was suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just kind of like a... again, on the same level as as like a Saturn has X amount of rings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It becomes an actual foundation of mindfulness, as the phrase says.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a liability, suffering, something that you just reason.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or it might be called...
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not concrete in the sense of something that you can focus on.
[SPEAKER_04]: So it's got...
[SPEAKER_04]: I want to say...
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not a sensation or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: But I mean, it's present.
[SPEAKER_04]: But what is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Just in colloquial terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, I want to say it's like a knowledge essence.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just as a word.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know that you're liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is something more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that knowledge can also still be abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's the difference between the knowledge that you now refer to and just telling yourself, I'm still liable to suffering?
[SPEAKER_03]: Somebody could just get convinced.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, in the same way that they're convinced of the level of external knowledge, I am liable to suffering, they could convince themselves I am not liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just based on, like, that you're given a list, this is what it means to be liable to suffering, and you check all the boxes, okay, that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Somebody gives you a different list, turns out you're not liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, that's why you can't convince someone to practice the dhammas.
[SPEAKER_00]: They have to see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: They have to see that, like, really, but what is it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, isn't this the same question as what is suffering?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, in a way, you could say.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which is fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in relation to what do you most acutely suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: Feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, yeah, on account of unpleasant feelings.
[SPEAKER_04]: Feelings.
[SPEAKER_03]: But is it like the liability itself?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it that it's on account of unpleasant feelings?
[SPEAKER_03]: In a way, you could say that, but isn't the liability itself a feeling as well?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to mystify like, oh, yeah, the liability to suffering is a kind of abstract entity.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's something that you feel as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because I find it's hard to think about suffering when you're
[SPEAKER_02]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, generally, feeling bad.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there is going to be something that you can look at readily.
[SPEAKER_03]: The thing is, it's there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you're not used to looking in that direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it...
[SPEAKER_03]: But you deep down know that if certain things were to happen, like, it's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That kind of vulnerability, if you can put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like you kind of
[SPEAKER_03]: Realize only once the things happen, because if if something, let's say, something that you, that is dear to you, were to suddenly be in danger, and you find out, it's not like after it goes away, after the thing, you lose it, then you will realize, oh, I'm suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's like immediately, when you find out this might happen,
[SPEAKER_00]: You already know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, basically, suffering is already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, which does mean that the more comfortable somebody's life is, and the more they generally get what they want, the harder it is to see this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they now need to make a deliberate effort in order to see that their good feelings and their moods depend on a host of things being there, taken for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're all, without exception, impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you don't see that, and you wait for that to fall apart, and only then do you realize that you have a problem, you have entirely overlooked the liability.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's quite common for people to be skeptical of the message of the Buddha and the Four Noble Truths, saying, what's all this talk about suffering now, the whole time?
[SPEAKER_01]: Mostly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, generally speaking, I'm doing quite okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they begin to rationalize just there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, okay, I understand 50 years from now I might be old, I might get sick, but I'll deal with it then.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a sort of common rationalization.
[SPEAKER_01]: Failing to see that now all sorts of things can happen and are happening that you are already running away from.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not even seeing that then.
[SPEAKER_03]: Realistically, you have to kind of bring it to the surface by thinking about certain things.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, it might even feel to you like, okay, I start suffering only when I think about death, or only when I think about aging, only when I think about sickness.
[SPEAKER_03]: From your initial perspective, it might seem that way.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you realize, the only reason why these reflections were able to trigger suffering, is because you were already in a state of suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just not as course as you're used to.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't have these specific signs that you expect.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you want to refine those recognitions and see, like, even the liability to suffering, the fact that nothing is happening right now,
[SPEAKER_03]: But anything, anything at all, could happen.
[SPEAKER_03]: It could upset my mind to any extent.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's suffering in itself, because you're not safe.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like... it's not something that you can entirely forget about.
[SPEAKER_03]: Your entire existence revolves around it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, whatever you're doing, no matter how small, is somehow related to the fact that you're vulnerable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and so hope and fear is another indication of this liability.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because why would you either fear or hope?
[SPEAKER_01]: Hope and fear go together, but why would you hope for or against something?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's only because you know that you are still liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't make that connection, you can say hope is a good thing, and then failing to see that as a sign of more work to be done.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, it's... you emphasize, let's say, the positive aspect of, yeah, when this thing that I want comes about.
[SPEAKER_03]: Failing to see that you wanting that thing,
[SPEAKER_03]: is the first problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, whether you're able to get it or not, that's now a separate thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that means being mindful of your liability to suffering, is being mindful of your feelings, or being mindful of your mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: But of course, like, because of the whole perversion of the views, people would put all the emphasis on the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, eh... like, for myself, I've rarely ever heard anybody speak about how you're mindful of your feelings, or how you're mindful of the mind, unless they can play feelings or sensations to make it much more palpable.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that whole dimension of how you feel,
[SPEAKER_03]: Without making it kind of objectified into sensations, it's almost impossible for people to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it is impossible for people to see, unless they've developed themselves in virtue, like not acting out of certain things, which are already rooted in all those feelings and mental states.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, when you don't act out of them, it's like the dust settles, let's say, and you're able to see, oh, this is what would have led me to act out.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it becomes clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, even in the suttas, you would see all the time, when people would come to ask the Buddha for advice on practicing mindfulness, he would start by saying you have to practice virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which, when for you, mindfulness is just observation, especially on the level of sensations,
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be... almost seem like unconnected.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, why do I have to...
[SPEAKER_00]: I could just start watching my sensations right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, that's evidence of the fact that what the Buddha is referring to as body is not what you think body is when you can practice mindfulness of it without virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's in that same direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: The body that matters, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's that direction that's underneath.
[SPEAKER_03]: The same way your mental state is not something that you can kind of pinpoint.
[SPEAKER_03]: The body that you're supposed to be mindful of is on that same level.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the body that undermines your ownership, not the body that you are relating to with your ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not even the body, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just kind of... yeah, perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's not even more... any more special, as I've said before, than just sounds and smells.
[SPEAKER_00]: That nobody tries to observe their body by smelling things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't make sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The possibility of ownership is also there only because of that more fundamental body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: The possibility of seeing, hearing, smelling, tasting, touching,
[SPEAKER_03]: Even thinking is there because of that body that you overlook and you descend onto the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you... that's why then, if you establish it, you wouldn't need to keep focusing on it, because sight, sound, smell, taste, touches are all secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That was the whole point.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you need to keep making your... like returning to the perceptions of it, as if those perceptions are it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you have recognized it to some extent, any of these things, the body, or liability to suffering, or hindrance, let's say, because that's also included, it doesn't say that you kind of... immediately, when you know a hindrance, the first thing you do is replace it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just think about something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, that's part of the satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowing the hindrances,
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowing how they arise, how they cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how would you, once you establish some context, prevent yourself from falling away from it, without constantly bringing it to mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: Realistically, you are gonna fall away from that, when you figure it out, the lecture ends.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your ability to not lose track of it is going to be, probably, proportionally related to how familiar you are with bringing yourself back to the point where you can't recognize it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh... Yeah, that still doesn't answer the question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't let you fall away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: What causes you to fall away from it, basically?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's...
[SPEAKER_05]: When you fall away from it, it's because you didn't see yourself acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And it's just like this lack of recognition, of just jumping into the content.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, you basically act out and you didn't see it, basically.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you fall away from it because you were a bit careless.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so, but, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you respond to that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you just determine harder next time that I will not distract myself?
[SPEAKER_05]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_05]: You have to recognize, like, as somebody said, like, more clear where the line of your responsibility is.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's kind of indirect, but in a way, it's very direct as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's kind of... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm saying that because, naturally, yes, you could recognize I fell away from it because I chose to attend to something else, but you also want to recognize it cannot be forced.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you cannot just, as a matter of...
[SPEAKER_00]: I decide now that I will not fall away from the content.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that thing that is making you fall away, practically speaking, is so close to you that you won't be able to, initially at least, see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, okay, here's the option to distract myself, so I won't choose it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a result of persistence, of noticing yourself falling back, and then bringing it back again, that's how you become less liable to falling away, because it's being reinforced.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, really, the reason why you fall away, even more accurately speaking, is because you still have an assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still have an assumption that allows for you to believe that the body isn't actually there.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you go to think about this or that, that the feeling is not there anymore, when you kind of distract yourself with entertainment or something that's going to take you away.
[SPEAKER_05]: Can we say, like, maybe a bit... maybe not... a bit abstract maybe, but can we say, like, falling away is what you are?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, actually, that's why it says, eh... based on assumption, you have being.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't fall away from the right perspective,
[SPEAKER_00]: You could see, at the very least, I may not be completely free from being, but that's the direction where being will increase.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's a sutta where, I think it's Majjhima too, where it says like, eh... understanding yoniso manasikāra means understanding how your attention, the things you attend to, lead to the increase
[SPEAKER_00]: of the influxes of sensuality, being, and ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think people read that line and it might seem kind of abstract, but it's factually that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you see being as a very kind of broad phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like the... you don't have like a sensation or an object of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a whole kind of overall situation that comes to be on account of you
[SPEAKER_00]: Emphasizing the content at the expense of that foundation, background foundation, that you have recognized.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's say you are established in the knowledge that you are right now liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have a mind that's factually liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not as a natural idea, but something that... a feeling there that you have recognized.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, what's going to happen?
[SPEAKER_04]: If you don't undermine that liability, that liability will be what is hooked.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that's your assumptions.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, but let's say you saw it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you're no longer kind of overlooking it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, let's say, for now, the assumption is not there, as strongly, at least, as it was before.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what happens next, basically?
[SPEAKER_05]: You ask if you need to do something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, because... like, is it going to stop there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you just remember it and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: My mind is established now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You saw it?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's there, factually.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what happens
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, that could be one option.
[SPEAKER_00]: That could be one option.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or let's say doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say, even before it becomes panic, let's say you have doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: I guess that's more what I mean, more so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, like, let's say, you're feeling like, okay, but is this really the liability?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you saw it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It was a feeling of
[SPEAKER_03]: Uncertainty, vulnerability, it's like, well, maybe if I do something, I can make this liability go away quicker or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or any sort of direction that the mind might try...
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, so that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: That was what I was aiming at with the question.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like, it will never feel like it's complete.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind will keep trying to convince you that you need to do more, you need to increase the awareness or something, and that's now the bait that's pulling you back into the content, even if it feels completely justified.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you would fall back into... like, you will increase your being from where it's at now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all the...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't engage with that content that the mind is trying to distract you with, you will find that it becomes harder and harder to go back to that background that you discerned initially.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the Buddha would say it's like a... like a... was it a quail or something?
[SPEAKER_03]: That should... in regards to the satipaṭṭhāna, it's like it goes into kind of like a hole.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then the hawk comes and tries to get it, but then it can't because, of course, it's a hawk.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not things for you to kind of just lose yourself in and just forget about everything else.
[SPEAKER_03]: The whole point is that things will be coming up, trying to
[SPEAKER_03]: Take you away from it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, eh... you want to see... you don't want to be kind of fighting those things by just, no, no, I won't think about these things.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'll just think about the... the... the body or the feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, they're not even on the same level.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you cannot just replace one with the other.
[SPEAKER_03]: Simply by staying with that recognition, that background, that pretty much undermines all of these things already,
[SPEAKER_03]: They become irrelevant on their own, without you having to kind of push them away.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because pushing them away would be another way of you involving yourself with them.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you saw that basis of your experience rightly, it wouldn't occur to you to involve yourself with these things, because it's just like...
[SPEAKER_03]: Kind of falling down from a higher place when you were already safer than you were when you engaged.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, it's about sinking, kind of hammering in the fact that even though it doesn't feel that way, even though there is still the assumption that the safety will come when I resolve the content,
[SPEAKER_03]: When I have the answer that I'm looking for... No.
[SPEAKER_03]: The safety is when I stay here and just, even if these things come up, I see through them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, I see them.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't just push them away.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't just kind of pretend that they don't exist.
[SPEAKER_03]: I see them in relation to this thing that I'm established in and I prioritize that, not the things.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what it means, like, you... by practicing satipaṭṭhāna, you give up covetousness and grief, as it's often translated, in regards to the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't say, oh, you just forget the world.
[SPEAKER_03]: It will keep coming up.
[SPEAKER_03]: It has to.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, through this, you purify yourself from any tendency to just lean in that direction, carelessly, again, and just...
[SPEAKER_00]: Almost by habit, prioritize anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's past, present, future, here, there, other people, yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't have to deny any of those things.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to make sure that you never put them first over the background, the foundation.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, like, now, even just the word foundation makes sense, but I remember when I first started to practice, like, meditation and stuff, they were talking about, like, foundation of mindfulness and stuff, and it was like... Why is the word foundation?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, like, why don't you look at your knee, not, like, look at the tree or something?
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like, why is that this one is a foundation?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's quite... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, actually, I think it's not an exaggeration to say that people basically ignore the other three.
[SPEAKER_00]: At best, it's like a theoretical explanation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, when you're in your meditation, you examine the dhammas or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not before that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't just see dhammas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, unless it kind of goes into, like, you get to the point where you're so advanced.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Watching the body that you can then start to watch your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereas it's the other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: That sutta of simile of the cook says, unless you have grasped the sign of the mind, you will be doing satipaṭ
[SPEAKER_05]: Unless you see your money, you can't see the money.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless you are composed in virtue and have the right view, you cannot develop satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It also says that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think there's something to say for the fact that, like, to an extent, some of these ideas won't be
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, it's not entirely obvious to me that acting out is like a kind of trying to step outside of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's not how it's gonna feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would see it as such, because can you actually step outside of the experience as a whole?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you were aware of that
[SPEAKER_00]: Even that idea, you'd say, like, no, this is not actually what I'm doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but it just seems like I'm stepping somewhere else in the experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, well, that's the assumption that you don't realize.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you were to be aware of that assumption, you wouldn't be able to have it, because it's ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it doesn't make sense.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's, it's, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: Really, you kind of start from the other way around.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you don't even see the assumption.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you might be told that this is what you're assuming.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you're just thinking in kind of logical terms, it's like, no, no, not like, how would I be doing that?
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's it's actually what you imply.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, any any time you bring yourself back, you realize, like, wait, this is, like, how is how is I overlooking this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's completely obvious in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: But
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, you don't get there by thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You get there by doing it, or by not doing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so that's the important point.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you will have to think about, when you lose it, you will have to, let's say, attend to your idea of what the body is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you've received right instructions, and you, to some extent, have some sense of where to look, that idea should not become secondary, because you actually discern the present
[SPEAKER_00]: That was the other thing I was going to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once that becomes established, that's the whole point of the... when the description of satipaṭṭhāna says, within the body, he sees the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within the feeling, he sees the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within the mind, he sees the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within phenomena, he sees phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... you will have your mind established,
[SPEAKER_00]: In a way, effortlessly, like, independent of your direct attention on one of these things.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, you will naturally be wanting to have thoughts about those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll want to be, like, clarifying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, what is that feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: And is it
[SPEAKER_00]: Did it come from here?
[SPEAKER_00]: Did it come from there?
[SPEAKER_00]: As Sutta says, is it made by somebody else?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it made by me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it random?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it made by both?
[SPEAKER_00]: What will I be tomorrow?
[SPEAKER_00]: What will it be tomorrow?
[SPEAKER_00]: What will it be later?
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole point is, within the presence of that feeling that's there, you see all of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see all of these ideas about feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you... then that's how you will transcend any views that you have in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you will see, wait, this actually comes first.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whether I say that it's made by me or it's made by somebody else, this is what comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you start to then imply, like, the feeling is the thing that will come from clarifying these ideas.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's kind of the assumption that you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the thing you're building.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, I will arrive at the feeling by clarifying these ideas.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, but that's where everyone starts from.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's what I said.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you have to, first, like, when you haven't seen it, you need to use these ideas.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you all, at the same time, need to be aware, like, okay, these are just kind of to point me towards where it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you're there, you might still have, well, very likely, will still have the tendency to think, like, all the ideas will help me.
[SPEAKER_00]: I need to keep, keep going, keep going.
[SPEAKER_00]: But no, it's like, right now, if you already established it, now you need to shift the order and see, okay, sure, I still have these ideas, but I need to now put this thing first that I have recognized.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean that those ideas need to disappear.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: And actually, that's how the ideas would become more accurate.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because then, they would be coming now from the right order, rather than just, kind of, piling up information together.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is that what's meant in some of the suttas, where it talks about, well, for instance, like the bodhisattva thinking, oh, well, all of this thinking is tiring, for example?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, no, I don't think it's that exact.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's more the conceivings that the suttas talk about.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think I'm...
[SPEAKER_02]: I forget exactly which suttas it is that talk about this, but... Majjhima 19, where it says, like, he's been cultivating thoughts of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Right, yeah, where he kind of realizes, like, this isn't necessary anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a slightly different...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's phenomenal now.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is in the context of jhāna and seeing that there's something more refined than even having the thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But these conceivings, not mistaking ideas of body, feeling, mind,
[SPEAKER_01]: And phenomena for those establishments that have to be there, regardless of which ideas you have, that's itself a different dhamma.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, actually, that's what he...
[SPEAKER_00]: In fact, it says there, he became established in jhāna when he realized these phenomena are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It explicitly says that, and people overlook that completely, and they think, oh, he became established in jhāna, means like he became perfectly focused on one single phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_03]: But no, it says he, after he was building up these thoughts of renunciation and planning his mind in that direction, he said, we realized this is not necessary anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: That doesn't mean he undid those phenomena and went elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_03]: It means he kind of established himself in a more fundamental intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: His intention was just to see, okay, these phenomena are there, instead of just trying to kind of keep doing them, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: The renunciation, the intention of renunciation, the wholesome mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have cultivated it already.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to keep building it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when he shifted on to, let's say, proper satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, in fact, many of the suttas would say, in order to develop satipaṭṭhāna, you first start by abandoning the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because those are the ones that are going to be obstructing your
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarity and making you conceive, even if you have the perfect intention not to do so.
[SPEAKER_00]: Conceive the ideas about the body for the present body that underlies those ideas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, once you've done away with the hindrances, which is what he was doing, like thinking when thoughts of sensuality would arise, he would think about the danger and all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, he was able to, almost effortlessly, have this clarity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, okay, phenomena are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because satipaṭṭhāna, in a way, is already the basis of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: So to say, like, it's the nimittas, the grounds of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's not like it's two separate things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I cultivate satipaṭṭhāna first, and then samādhi comes.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being able to have perspective over the body is already a level of samādhi that you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Might not be the first jhāna, but it's already
[SPEAKER_00]: That aspect, it's a unification.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind is unified in that background thing and isn't as much kind of scattered among the content that still arises.